<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached near Exeter on Cant. c. vi. v. 13 being an exhortation to all Protestant dissenters to joyn together against popery.</title>
            <author>Tanner, Thomas, 1630-1682.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1677</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 67 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A62739</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T146</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R1224</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12626294</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12626294</idno>
            <idno type="VID">64659</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A62739)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 64659)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 336:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached near Exeter on Cant. c. vi. v. 13 being an exhortation to all Protestant dissenters to joyn together against popery.</title>
                  <author>Tanner, Thomas, 1630-1682.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 26, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Henry Brome ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1677.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title: A call to the Shulamite.</note>
                  <note>"The epistle dedicatory" signed: Tho. Tanner.</note>
                  <note>Advertisement: p. [1] at end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Song of Solomon VI, 13 --  Sermons.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:64659:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preached near EXETER: On CANT. <hi>c.</hi> vi. <hi>v.</hi> 13. BEING AN EXHORTATION TO ALL Proteſtant Diſſenters To joyn together againſt POPERY.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's device with crown surmounting cannon</figDesc>
               <head>H B</head>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Henry Brome,</hi> at the Gun at the Weſt End of St. <hi>Paul's.</hi> 1677.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:64659:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:64659:2"/>
            <head>To the Honourable, The Lady <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RITH POLE,</hi> The Virtuous Conſort of Sir <hi>COURTENAY POLE,</hi> Baronet, Colonel-General of the Eaſtern Diviſion of <hi>Devon,</hi> a Member of the Parliament, &amp;c.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>MADAM,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>Our Ladiſhip heard this <hi>Call of the Shulamite</hi> with a pious ſympathy, and compaſsion; and ſince it took ſo well with you in the hearing, the firſt view of it is in gratitude returned to Your Ladiſhip's hand, and eye, that you may trie whether it be not the ſame that it was. And becauſe this <hi>Call</hi> did not ſound alike to every ear, but was judged of, as every head was more clear, or full of pre-poſſeſsion: and could not reach to others, to whom it was more eſpecially intended, but by the Eccho's of a ſiniſter report: I muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs I was not hard to be induced upon ſome per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion,
<pb facs="tcp:64659:3"/>to let it go unto the Preſs, that I might have a few Copies to diſtribute among ſome of theſe (in hope that their apprehenſions might be ſome wayes rectified, or reduced by them) with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any further trouble to my ſelf. So praying to Your Ladiſhip an encreaſe of all the bleſsings of this life; and at laſt, that full of years, and good works (which are your only ſtudies) You may ſweetly drop into a better; being that, that You do infinitely more deſire. I humbly beg Your Ladi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip's pardon, and protection too,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>MADAM,</salute>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your very humble and obliged Servant,</hi> Tho. Tanner.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:64659:3"/>
            <head>A CALL TO THE SHULAMITE.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Cant. 6.13.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Return, return, ô <hi>Shulamite,</hi> return, return, that we may look upon thee: what ſhall ye ſee in the <hi>Shulamite?</hi> as it were the company of two armies.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>ET us take that for granted, which will hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be denied us on any hand (or if it be, the majority of Interpreters will over-rule it) that this Song of Excellency ſetteth forth the paſſionate deſires of the Church after Chriſt, and the moſt affectionate returns of Chriſt himſelf towards Her. But in the words which I have read, he doth not only ſhew his own affection in his Call after the wandring <hi>Shulamite,</hi> but that of his Body too, which is the ſame Chriſt myſtical; ſaying, <hi>Return, return, that we may look upon thee,</hi> plainly intimating that there is more than one in this Call: And no one will deny, or doubt, but that the ingeminating of the words doth expreſs the greater ardour and elegancy of intention. Wherefore for the better opening of the words, let us. 1. conſider the Call, what it is, <hi>viz.</hi> to <hi>return,</hi> 2. The Perſon called, who ſhe is, <hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>Shulamite.</hi> 3. The
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:64659:4"/>End, <hi>that we may look upon thee.</hi> 4. The Anſwer of the <hi>Shu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamite; what will ye ſee in the Shulamite?</hi> 5. The Rejoinder: <hi>as it were the company of two armies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, for the Call what it is; It is to <hi>riturn,</hi> implying that the <hi>Shulamite</hi> was ſome time before in the right way, if ſhe had but held it: Elſe it had been rather ſaid, <hi>Come hither, come hither, ô Shulamite:</hi> but it is, <hi>Return, return:</hi> ſhe had left the way that before ſhe was engaged in: And the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gemination in the Call ſeemeth to import, that ſince ſhe went off, ſhe occaſioned much trouble to the Church, and as much inconveniency to her ſelf; ſo that the ſaving of more trouble to the Church was a juſt motive to make her call out unto the <hi>Shulamite;</hi> and the compaſſion of her made it more intenſe and earneſt: for the Church loved the <hi>Shulamite,</hi> and wiſhed her well-doing, even as her own.</p>
            <p>Secondly, for the perſon called therefore, and called the <hi>Shulamite,</hi> who or what was ſhe? ſome underſtand her to be the Church of the Gentiles, called upon by the Synagogue, or Church of the Jews to return, that is, to joyn her ſelf to the Jewiſh Congregation, and to worſhip with her: but as we hinted before, <hi>Return</hi> ſignifies, that the <hi>Shulamite</hi> was once in the right way; which could not be ſaid of the Gentiles in the time of <hi>Solomon,</hi> if at any time before. Others therefore take the <hi>Shulamite</hi> to be the beloved wife of <hi>Solomon,</hi> and that her name doth ſeem to be framed out of his, for the more ingra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiating of <hi>Shelomoh</hi> with <hi>Shulamith,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> and <hi>Shulamith</hi> with <hi>She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomoh,</hi> (as if he had called her the <hi>Shelomah,</hi> but one entirely with my ſelf.) This <hi>Shulamite</hi> is therefore thought to be the Daughter of <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> who to gain the greater power with her Husband, became Proſelyre to the Jewiſh Church; but being her ſelf unſtedfaſt in the Covenant, proved an occaſion to draw away, the heart of <hi>Solomon</hi> to worſhip in the High places, wherewith the Lord was offended. Thus we find in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, that from divers literal and hiſtorical hints of paſſages many things purely ſpiritual, and myſtical, have been ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to a more general, and univerſal intention, and ſo conveyed to the Church: which we ſee almoſt in all the types relating to our Savioir Chriſt, as they are exhibited and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emplified
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:64659:4"/>in the New Teſtament. Let the <hi>Shulamite</hi> (then) be the diverted Proſelyte, once a Member of the true Church; and let this voice, <hi>Return, return,</hi> be either that of <hi>Solomon,</hi> converted from his own error, and now calling upon the <hi>Shu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamite</hi> (in the name of Chriſt) and longing to reclaim her; Or that of the Daughters of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> (in the name of the true Church) longing alſo to regain her. <hi>Return, return, ô Shulamite,</hi> from thy High-places, and from thy divers Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips, according to thine own inventions, and readjoyn thy ſelf to us, <hi>Return, return.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, To this end, <hi>That we may look upon thee:</hi> that is, that we may both contemplate and admire thy taking beauty, and enjoy it as our own, even as we did before. <hi>Return, ô Shulamite, return;</hi> we acknowledg the ſplendor of thy vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues; oh that they were ours once again! we adore thy piety; oh that it were well informed! we admire the variety of thy gifts and graces, which are thy rare embelliſhments; oh that thou mayeſt not have received them to thine own, and our prejudice! <hi>Return, ô Shulamite, return,</hi> that we may look upon thee in ſuch a manner as we earneſtly deſire, <hi>viz.</hi> as our own entirely, without diviſion.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, Then we have the Anſwer of the <hi>Shulamite:</hi> what ſhall ye ſee in the <hi>Shulamite?</hi> It ſeems to be a kind of ſhye and coy anſwer, caſt (as it were) with half a look; as if ſhe had ſaid, I know well enough that you do but compli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and flatter with me; you have no ſuch opinion of my accompliſhments and beauties as you pretend, nor any ſuch deſire of my company; why ſhould you diſſemble ſo? for what can you ſee in the <hi>Shulamite</hi> that can be taking unto you, that are of another way, and fancy other looks than ſuch as the <hi>Shulamites?</hi> Some do joyn the latter part to this: <hi>as it were the company of two armies, viz.</hi> that are jealous of one another: <hi>(q. d.)</hi> If I ſhould return again to you, we ſhould never be ſatisfied one in the other, we ſhould be alwaies at debate and ready to break out into battels: Better aſunder as we are!</p>
            <p>Fifthly, But I take theſe laſt words, as the Rejoynder of the true Church, or daughters of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> replying again to the <hi>Shulamite;</hi> If thou wilt but return unto us, we ſhall be
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:64659:5"/>ſtrong, <hi>as it were the company of two armies</hi> againſt a common enemy: or we ſhall make a beauteous or a ſplendid ſhew, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven as one Army drawn up into two Diviſions, when the Prince is to paſs thorough them in triumphant manner, as is uſed after Victory. <hi>Return, return</hi> therefore, <hi>ô Shulamite, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn, return,</hi> that we may behold thy beauty, enjoy thy love, and joyn thy ſtrength and thine array to ours, and we ſhall be both happy.</p>
            <p>The reſult of the words, thus opened, is only this.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That the true Church doth earneſtly deſire the return of her ſcattered and divided Members.</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
               </label>
            </p>
            <p>When God had ſtirred up his people to unite and joyn themſelves from all parts againſt the Canaanites, is there not mention made of <hi>Ephraim,</hi> and <hi>Benjamin,</hi> and <hi>Zebulun,</hi> and <hi>Iſſachan,</hi> and <hi>Nepthali,</hi> that aſſembled? But is it not alſo ſaid, <hi>for the diviſions of Reuben there were great thoughts or impreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of heart;
<note place="margin">Judg. 5. &amp;c.</note> for the diviſions of Reuben there were great ſearchings of heart;</hi> that is, much trouble and ſorrow, much enquiring what the reaſon ſhould be, that <hi>Reuben</hi> ſhould ſo divide it ſelf from the body of the Holy People? <hi>And why ſhould Gilead abide beyond Jordan, and Dan remain in ſhips? why ſhould Aſher continue in his Ports or Creeks?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When the ten Tribes did rend themſelves from the obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of the Sons of <hi>David,</hi> and from the Worſhip of the true Temple, built by <hi>Solomon</hi> according unto God's appointment, do we not read of ſuch complaints as theſe?
<note place="margin">Jer. 2.3, 5.</note> 
               <hi>Iſrael was holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs unto the Lord, and what iniquity, ſaith the Lord, have your fathers found in me, that they are gone far from me, and have walked after vanity,
<note place="margin">Hoſ. 14.1. &amp;c.</note> and are become vain? O Iſrael re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn unto the Lord thy God, for thou haſt fallen by thine ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity. Take unto you words, and return unto the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And is not this the great Promiſe to ſupport the ſpirits of the true Worſhippers?
<note place="margin">Jer. 23.3.4.</note> 
               <hi>I will gather my Flock; I will ſet up ſhepheards over them. Becauſe ye are all become droſs, behold I will therefore gather you into the midſt of Jeruſalem.</hi> And abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of ſuch other Prophecies, which may be more cloſe and pertinent, is to be left to your obſervations, when you read the holy Scriptures.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:64659:5"/>
            <p>To come to the times of the New Teſtament, when there were diviſions in the Church of <hi>Corinth,</hi> doth not <hi>Paul</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt after this manner. <hi>I beſeech you, brethren,
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 1.10. &amp;c.</note> by the name of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, that ye all ſpeak the ſame thing, that there be no diviſions among you, but that ye be perfectly joyned to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in the ſame mind, and in the ſame judgment.</hi> To the Church of the <hi>Galatians</hi> thus:
<note place="margin">Gal. 1.6, 7.</note> 
               <hi>I marvel that ye are ſo ſoon removed from him, that called you into the grace of Chriſt, unto another Goſpel; which is not another, but that there be ſome that trouble you. O fooliſh Galatians, who hath bewitched you?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gal. 3.1. Eph. 4.1, &amp;c.</note> To the <hi>Epheſians</hi> thus: <hi>I the priſoner of the Lord beſeech you that ye walk worthy of the vocation wherewith you are called, endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring to keep the unity of the ſpirit in the bond of peace; for there is one Body, and one Spirit, one Lord, one Faith, one Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, &amp;c.</hi> To the <hi>Philippians</hi> thus:
<note place="margin">Phil. 2.1. &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>If there be any conſolation in Chriſt fulfil my joy, that ye be like-minded, having the ſame love, being of one accord, of one mind.
<note place="margin">Phil. 3.15, 16.</note> Let as many as be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect be thus minded, and if in any thing ye be otherwiſe minded, God ſhall reveal even this unto them. Nevertheleſs whereto we have already attained, let us walk by the ſame rule, let us mind the ſame thing.</hi> It might but ſeem ſuperfluous to run through the reſt of the Epiſtles, which are all full of the like expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions.</p>
            <p>To proceed to the times ſucceeding the Apoſtles, while yet the Church was under perſecution. About the year of our Lord 199. Becauſe the <hi>Eaſtern</hi> Churches held reſolutely to the obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of the Feaſt of <hi>Eaſter,</hi> at the ſame time that the Jews kept the Paſſover; which the <hi>Weſtern</hi> Chriſtians were offend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at, not becauſe they doubted whether the Feaſt ſhould be celebrated in memory of our Saviours reſurrection (which it ſeems had been alwaies uſed, without any interruption from the times of the Apoſtles) but becauſe they thought it not convenient to have this day kept on any other than that when our Saviour roſe; whereas if they had obſerved the falling of the 14th Moon, they ſhould not only have gratified the Jews, but might have happened to obſerve the wrong time: And we do not doubt but the <hi>Weſtern</hi> Chriſtians were in the right: But becauſe the <hi>Eaſtern</hi> Churches were reſolute in their own
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:64659:6"/>way, one <hi>Victor,</hi> Biſhop at that time of <hi>Rome</hi> (who was emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent on this ſide of the world, in as much as <hi>Rome</hi> was the Imperial City, and the number and quality of Chriſtians there, was predominant) took upon him to ſever from the union of Communion all the <hi>Eaſtern</hi> Churches which adhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to the other Cuſtom: Behold the firſt print of the foot of <hi>Antichriſt!</hi> here was a beginning of erecting a falſe Church, excommunicating for an opinion, or for a practice, which was indifferent, or at leaſt not inconſiſtent with the peace of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians; excommunicating not only one perſon, or a few par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars, but whole Churches at a blow; yea, all Churches, though they were on this ſide, and of the ſame Communion, if they would not joyn in the ſame wrong; for which fact the ſaid <hi>Victor</hi> was ſharply (then) reproved by <hi>Ireneus</hi> Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Lyons</hi> in <hi>France</hi> (and a better man than he) where there was alſo a numerous and a noble Church of <hi>Weſtern</hi> Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians.
<note place="margin">Euſeb. l. 5. cap. 26.</note> It is the falſe Church therefore which is for ſcattering and dividing, whereas the true Church is for gathering and uniting as much as may be; And although the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> did afterwards reſume ſome policy, or prudence, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der other Biſhops, inclining to a ſhew of moderation; yet the breach, as only skinned over, hath broken out again, and laſteth unto this day, and will laſt for ever, till <hi>Rome</hi> return to be what it was before this breach of unity and charity: upon her therefore we juſtly lay the impeachment of the firſt great Schiſm that ever was, wherein ſhe ſtill perſiſteth, think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by her power to bear all other Churches down, while ſhe aſſumeth to her ſelf the name of <hi>Catholick,</hi> and impoſeth on the reſt the name of <hi>Schiſmaticks.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Again about the year of our Lord 254. when the Perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion under <hi>Decius</hi> waxed hot, many poor ſouls ſtaggered by reaſon of the peril, and were forced by fear to comply ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what with the Heathen Sacrificers, which much afflicted them in their conſciences; and they afterwards moſt humbly ſought the peace of the Church, and to be reſtored to her Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion. But one <hi>Novatus</hi> a Presbyter oppoſed their reſtitution, and upon the queſtion raiſed a diviſion in the Church, and after that, pretending unto more purity, erected another
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:64659:6"/>Church (if ſuch a pretenſion may be but ſo named) in oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition to the General Aſſembly, calling themſelves the Church of Martyrs. So did he ſeek to ſcatter or divide thoſe poor Members, which the Church would have gathered and ſet in joynt by repentance and confeſſion, and ſuch holy diſcipline as was neceſſary both to comfort them in reſpect of the time paſt, and to confirm them for the time to come: and many of theſe that were thus reſtored became afterwards conſtant even unto the death. It was to be known therefore by the point of charity, if there were no other evidence, which was the true Church; and the other hath left to this day (by the ſpecial providence of God) the mark of hereſie and ſchiſm upon it ſelf, which is never to be obliterated.</p>
            <p>Once again, and ſo to ſurceaſe from further inſtances: About the year of our Lord 356. towards the latter end of the reign of <hi>Conſtantine</hi> (the Perſecution having long ceaſed, for his Reign was long) there aroſe one <hi>Donatus,</hi> who wrote ſomewhat after the copy of <hi>Novatus</hi> and the <hi>Arians,</hi> ſupply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the reſt by occaſion, intereſt, the humour of the <hi>Africans,</hi> and his own ambition: He condemned other Churches as im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pure, rebaptized ſuch as joyned unto him, and entitled ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation unto them alone: And theſe have alſo left the like mark and brand upon their followers for ever.</p>
            <p>Let the Sects of latter times, whoſe names I ſpare, repute amongſt themſelves, or give account to the world (if they think fit) what their judgment is concerning theſe Parties, or thoſe Churches; or what they think concerning this An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquity whereof we ſpeak, which is of the firſt and beſt times (if there be any to be approved in their ſenſe) or concerning the poſterity that is to come, what they think, or what theſe would have them judge (or whether they make any matter of it) about themſelves.</p>
            <p>I have done with the in-artificial arguments (that are ſo called) which yet ſhould be the ſtrongeſt, by reaſon of ſuch authority, whereon they do rely; but that power and autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity may not be divided from one another, which thoſe that are given to diviſion do affect; and that you may the better hold my method (whilſt I my ſelf do not ſhew to affect di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viding
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:64659:7"/>from the common way) I proceed to the reaſons of the point. If you would know why the true Church doth ſo earneſtly deſire the return of her ſcattered and divided Members: ſome of her reaſons are theſe that follow.</p>
            <p>The firſt is the unity of the ſpirit,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>1</label> that doth inſpire the whole body, enforcing unto unity, love, and ſympathy (mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually and reciprocally) in all the Members. This unity of the ſpirit is the great and earneſt deſire that is put into the hearts of all Saints in their converſion to ſave themſelves and others,
<note place="margin">1 Tim. 4.15.</note> and to edifie one another in their moſt holy faith. Now becauſe there is but one way to ſave our ſelves, and the ſame is the way to ſave others alſo; this maketh the deſire of the Church the more intenſe to gather, and to bind unto it ſelf all that do belong unto the election of grace: To en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighten them that are yet in darkneſs, to confirm the weak, to ſtir up them that faint, and are like to yield to wearineſs, and to reduce them that go aſtray; for there is but one Lord, one Faith, one Hope, one Baptiſm, and one Truth. The way to ſave our ſelves is to walk in this Unity by one and the ſame ſpirit; ſo that we come to ſave others by the ſame Acts where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we ſave our ſelves; and by the Communion of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy come to receive thoſe benefits which we could not attain unto by a ſolitary faith, or private life. Wherefore the deſires of the Church for unity cannot but be intenſe and earneſt, being thus converſant about the common ſalvation, which is much endangered and diſturbed by diviſion; inſomuch that even they that are in the right way can ſcarcely be ſaved, by reaſon of the breaches, impairments and decayes of piety, which the others make.</p>
            <p>Now true it is, that this one ſpirit, which is given unto all that do believe, is diſtributed amongſt them according to va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riety of gifts and meaſures; but the ſame that <hi>are given unto every one to profit</hi> himſelf; the ſame are alſo given unto him to edifie another; whether they be gifts of knowledge, or gifts of grace (as they uſe to diſtinguiſh the gifts of ſanctity from any other kind) <hi>God hath dealt to every man the meaſure of faith,
<note place="margin">Ro. 12, 3. &amp;c.</note> and we are every one members one of another, having gifts differing according to the grace that is given to us, according to
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:64659:7"/>the proportion of faith.</hi> And,
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 12.4. &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>the manifeſtation of the ſpirit is given unto every man to profit withal: There are diverſities of giftes; but the ſame ſpirit: God hath ſo tempered the body together, that one member ſhall have need of another, that there ſhould be no ſchiſm in the body; but that the members ſhould have the ſame care one for another.</hi> And again it is ſaid,
<note place="margin">Eph. 4 11. &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>that there are divers gifts given for the perfecting of the Saints, for the edifying of the body of Chriſt, till we all come in the unity of the faith, and of the knowledg of the Son of God unto per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect men, unto the meaſure of the ſtature of the fulneſs of Chriſt. That ſpeaking the truth in love, we may grow up into him in all things, which is the head, even Chriſt, from whom the whole body fitly joyned together, and compacted by that which every joynt ſupplieth, according to the effectual working in the meaſure of every part, maketh encreaſe of the body unto the edifying of it ſelf in love.</hi> From which, and many other paſſages in the writings of this Apoſtle, that which we have ſaid may ſeem to be abundantly proved; and many other things might be inferred, and applied, fit to be ſeriouſly conſidered, and layed to heart: as <hi>viz.</hi> That the gifts and graces of private men are not only profitable, but neceſſary to the Church, as well as thoſe of her Miniſters, or Elders; and that the meaſures of faith, and hope, and love, and zeal are diſtrubted unto every one, according to the exigency of the Church, the Body, which is the fulneſs of Chriſt; and that by ſuch graces we are more ſtrongly joyned unto one another, than by any other gifts, though they be of miracles; That one Member cannot want another, or divide it ſelf from the Body, but that a rent and ſchiſm will follow in the Body; not without great ſin and miſchief; for ſuch a rent is a ſin againſt the Head, dividing the unity of the ſpirit; againſt the body, hindring of its growth wounding it with pain, maiming it with impotency, depriving it of perfection: againſt particular members, in that it doth with-draw that meaſure whereby another mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber ſhould have been ſupplied, and doth drain and divert the fulneſs of Chriſt; againſt a mans own ſoul, in that as a branch cut off from the Vine, he muſt needs become dry, ceaſe to be fruitful, and grow worſe and worſe, till he return back to be
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:64659:8"/>a new engrafted. In a word, if one man cannot grow in Chriſt, whilſt another is at a ſtand, or doth decay and wither; and the very juice and chyle that doth adminiſter unto growing be ſpeaking of the ſame truth; and the only way of digeſting this truth, <hi>to making encreaſe of the body,</hi> be the <hi>edifying of it ſelf in love:</hi> We may eaſily perceive how this unity of the ſpirit doth conſtrain the Church, if it be poſſible, to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain the unity of her Body; for ſhe cannot keep the unity of ſpirit without it; but if ſhe cannot poſſibly do ſo, then ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly to deſire and endeavour the return of her ſcattered and divided Members.</p>
            <p>Now to ſay the truth, the diſſenting Brethren have been al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies ſenſible of the weight of this argument, and to break the force, or rebate the edge of it, they pretend divers matters (as it were for their excuſe, ſince it cannot be denied but we were firſt a Church, or elſe they could not have derived from Us, as they do; and that we were the firſt in poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the faith) as <hi>viz.</hi> 1. That they agree with Us in the unity of faith, believing the ſame Doctrine of ſalvation. 2. In the unity of the ſpirit, having the ſame deſires a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the ſaving of themſelves and others, 3. In the bond of charity, as we are all members (they ſay) of the ſame Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Church; and as Proteſtant Profeſſors, members of one another. 4. Then that variety of opinion, and union in the point of charity, are not inconſiſtent. 5. Nay, that divers Order, Diſcipline, and Communion need not break the bond of charity, unleſs by accident of mens corruptions; which if they ſhould be obſerved and humoured, the Goſpel it ſelf could never have been preached; for our Lord foretold, that it would be an occaſion of diviſion. 6. And for ſchiſm right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly underſtood, that they look upon it as an heinous ſin, even as we do. In which ſeveral pretences, as they give us little cauſe of ſatisfaction; ſo they give us a juſt and neceſſary oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of returning ſomewhat more than is like to ſort to their favour.</p>
            <p>We muſt confeſs; that when the Church is ſo divided, that in the judgment of charity, many godly perſons do divide themſelves from the body; and in the judgment of the Church,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:64659:8"/>many men of eminent gifts and graces (that were known to be ſuch whilſt they remained in her communion) do deſert her communion, it cannot but prove an inexplicable inconve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nience both to the Church and Them: for if all believe and teach the ſame Doctrine of Salvation, whence ariſeth ſo much caution whom we hear? ſuch exceptions, heats, and ſcruples? If we do not all believe the ſame Doctrine, as it is to be doubted that we do not, for as much as there ſeemeth not only to be a divers ſcope and drift in the preſſing of many points of impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, but that we fear our diſſenting Brethren do not cloſe with Us in one of the 12 articles of the Apoſtles Creed (though ſome of them do not ſcruple at ſtanding up when the whole is rehearſed in our Churches) <hi>viz. I believe the Holy Catholick Church, the Communion of Saints,</hi> putting ſuch a conſtruction upon it as is far from the conſent not onely of our Church, but of all Ages, as we conceive: I ſay, how can we then <hi>grow up together into him in all things, which is the head, even Chriſt, from whom the whole body is fitly joyn'd toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther unto one encreaſe?</hi> If they could hold ſtill the ſame charity inviolable, without the ſame Order, Diſcipline, and Communion (as others do pretend) whence ſhould ariſe ſuch animoſities and contentions? It cannot be altogether from mens corruptions, as at the firſt propagation of the Goſpel: but if it do ariſe partly from the corruptions, frailties, and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tialities of ſuch as break without neceſſity, partly from the paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of ſuch as are offended juſtly (as we conceive, howſoever unjuſt or extravagant they may be, when they are provoked.) let them joyn the whole verſe together; <hi>It is neceſſary that offences come, but wo be to them by whom they come.</hi> But, as we conceive, the nature of the thing it ſelf doth neceſſarily infer a breach of charity (ſuppoſe men more good or perfect than either They or We can find, or our Anceſtors before us, or the Poſterity to come) for it cannot be, that there ſhould be two Communions, wherein it is ſuppoſed to be unlawful for one to joyn with another, but that one Party to the other muſt needs be as the <hi>Jew</hi> or the <hi>Samaritan.</hi> But if it be granted, that theſe two parties cannot poſſibly have perfect charity with one another (which if the nature of the thing did not hinder,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:64659:9"/>the juſt judgements of God, by reaſon of the violation of his own Ordinance would do it; then it muſt needs follow, that the <hi>body cannot edifie it ſelf in love:</hi> and ſo the Church muſt needs retain an earneſt deſire to be reſtored to its beſt eſtate, when it was in Union: for though we may remain (poſſibly) Members of the Catholick Church ſtill, yet becauſe we doubt of our conſent in the Catholick Faith, we cannot be u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nited, nor joyn in perfect charity; and though we be all <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants,</hi> and ſo members of one another, we can take no greater benefit or priviledg thereby, than <hi>Engliſh</hi> men, when they are in civil wars with one another.</p>
            <p>To deal ingeniouſly this is the charity of the Church; ſhe looketh upon ſuch good men (whom in charity we way eſteem ſo, in ſome meaſure) as do divide and ſeparate from Us, and ſuch as they may draw with them, to belong to the body ſtill; not only of the Catholick Church, but of ſuch particular Churches from which they do recede, or within whoſe Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cincts they may chance to fall: Therefore ſhe is not raſh to excommunicate them, but uſeth all her care, and power, and tenderneſs to reclaim and to reduce them, having arms ever open to embrace them, and to reſtore them to her peace, and to indulge them in what ſhe may, to oblige them the faſter to her ſelf. So far are we from looking upon them as other Churches, or that their ſchiſms can make them ſuch; or as free from our charge, though they renounce Us; or as fallen from the hope of the Goſpel, with all their followers, into an inevitable ſtate of damnation, though we cannot reduce them (as the Papiſts judge of Us) that we own, even theſe, as a part of the Church of <hi>England</hi> againſt their wills, and are ever ready to regain their good will, and to reduce them to a better ſtate: for, though we ſpeak it ſoft, and mildly, we do judg indeed, that theſe do much interrupt and diſturb, the way of ſalvation to themſelves and others, and do much impeach and prejudice thoſe amongſt our ſelves, who before did run well; and would yet proceed to do ſo, if they did not object their rubbs and impediments in the way.</p>
            <p>We anſwer further, that whereas it is truely ſaid, [<hi>Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onum varietas, &amp; opinantium unitas non ſunt</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>;] Varie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:64659:9"/>of opinions, and unity of Opiners are not inconſiſtent; Our Church alloweth a greater latitude in this kind, than any of thoſe that do pretend a latitude, only to palliate their own re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraints: for amongſt them, if one be for Lay-Elders, and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other againſt it; one for the power of Paſtors, another for the power of the People; one for laying on of hands after bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, and another againſt it; nay, one for free-will, and ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for free-grace: and ſo in certain leſſer queſtions, it hath been found enough to divide and ſub-divide them into Parties, Churches, feuds, and animoſities; whereas in our Church great variety of opinions may, and do conſiſt very well with the Unity of the Church: Every Scholar knows how in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genious men do abound in their own ſenſes, even in the Schools: and it is not at all to the prejudice of the Church, but may be rather to her benefit, that certain points be not carried (other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe) in extremes, but that there may be here a little and there a little, and one to ballance with another. But when this rule of variety or diverſity of opinion is traduced to a contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riety of eſtabliſhment, they muſt give us leave to aſſume that ſuch a diverſity is utterly inconſiſtent with the Unity of the Church. In vain therefore do they declaim in general againſt ſchiſm, as much as we could wiſh, being ſenſible of what <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>melius</hi> hath delivered, <hi>viz.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Schiſmatis no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men in Eccleſia ſemper ignomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nioſum, publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> damnatum.</hi> In Tert. de praeſcript. ad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Haeret.</note> that <hi>the name of ſchiſm hath been alwaies ignominious in the Church, and on all hands con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned,</hi> whilſt they defend in particular all the Sects at this day (beſides the Quakers) to be true particular Churches, that a man may ſafely joyn with any of them, <hi>to do better,</hi> that ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration is no ſchiſm; that the Church which impoſeth (though it be but things indifferent) is the ſchiſmatical Church, if it will not vary from her orders, for the ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the weak, or ſcrupulous: and that in ſuch caſes the ſchiſmatical Churches (which are ſo called) are the truer and purer Churches of Chriſt, and have all Church power within themſelves, to all intents and purpoſes: for where can we now find a Schiſm which is culpable? or a Church which can ſtand, if ſhe muſt vary from her order upon all demands? or any poſſibility either of a Church or of a Schiſm? By all which it ſeems that ſome of our diſſenting Brethren do miſdoubt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
<pb facs="tcp:64659:10"/>as lyable unto this charge of ſchiſm, and would either cloak it neatly, if they could, or if it come to the worſt, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend that ſchiſm is no ſuch ſin, as they ſometimes granted; and that they may lawfully live in ſchiſm, eſpecially when their maintenance ariſeth that way (as ſome have put them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves upon that exegency, and ſo are bound to maintain that which maintaineth them, framing their lives and doctrines ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their intereſts.) Not to grate any further upon that point, wherein they are ſo tender; there remaineth yet another word about the Unity of the Spirit, that they have the ſame deſires (if not more intenſe and earneſt than we our ſelves) for the good of ſouls, for the ſaving of themſelves and others: We do not doubt but that there is a zeal of God amongſt many of them, though not according unto a right knowledge; not becauſe they are more weak or ignorant than We, but only otherwiſe perſwaded or inclined (howſoever it hath happened to them.) We truſt that many of them do ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely mean as they profeſs: And ſo far as this is true, we acknowledge the working of one and the ſame ſpirit in them and Us: We look upon them as a part of the body, and wherein they are not only not againſt Us, but for Us, that they are ſo far One with us. But then, if they do really be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that we have the ſame ſpirit amongſt us (or ſome of us at leaſt) why ſhould they ſo magnifie the ſame ſpirit in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves above the ſame in Us? as if there were not the ſame power and purity of the ſpirit amongſt Us to conveigh grace unto the hearers, or to make them perfect that do come unto Us? which Query we have the more reaſon to put home to our Brethren, ſince they may ſeem (now) to ceaſe from their inſtance upon the work of converſion (a gift which they thought almoſt ſingular to themſelves before) as a thing below their Auditories; or to preach againſt prophaneneſs (where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they were once the <hi>Boanerges's</hi> of the Age) ſeeing their fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers muſt be taken for no ſuch; and, it may be, cannot well bear it; ſo that all their writings of late (which are the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports of their Preachments to ſuch as cannot hear them) do run in a new ſtrain, which is much different from that way, which they did admire and applaud before. Again, if they
<pb facs="tcp:64659:10"/>do acknowledg ſuch an Unity of Spirit with. Us, how can they think or pretend (as they do) to be compleat without Us, and to have no need of Us?
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 12.15. &amp;c.</note> how happeneth it that they do ſo little weigh what the Apoſtle ſaith, that <hi>one member hath need of another? And if the foot ſhall ſay, becauſe I am not the hand, I am not of the body; is it therefore not of the body? And if the ear ſhall ſay, becauſe I am not the eye I am not of the body, is it therefore not of the body? The eye cannot ſay unto the hand, I have no need of thee: Nor again the head to the feet, I have no need of you. That there ſhould be no ſchiſm in the body, but the members ſhould have the ſame care one for another.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But if theſe members ſeparate from the body, can each mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber which is ſeparated ſubſiſt by it ſelf? or any few that joyn together, preſently conſtitute themſelves an entire Body, a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plete Church? Or can any of their Officers, which was but as an hand or a foot before make it ſelf an heart or an head in a New Church, and think that in truth they are ſuch, if they be not altogether uſeleſs?
<note place="margin">Judg. 9.15.</note> which cannot but put us in mind of <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tham</hi>'s Parable, and though we ſhall abſtain from applying the prickles of it to our Brethren, yet we doubt that it is this ambition of ſome hand, or foot, or other, which thinks it ſelf worthy of a better place, that is one of the ſad occaſions of ſuch diſmembring. But when they have diſmembred and divided to the utmoſt, let others obſerve that the uſe whereof they are (if they be of any good uſe) is but the ſame, of which they were before in their proper places; and being diſtorted to the places, which they uſurp, they do but move like members our of joynt, and will ſoon be impaired for want of the body, notwithſtanding their pretences to completeneſs among them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. And we could ſhew of how little uſe men of eminent gifts and parts before have been for many years, ſince they left their ſtations in the Church; the leaving of us (as we conceive) occaſioning the dereliction of the ſpirit unto them; ſo that they are left to themſelves in matters of great concern to their own good, and the good of others.</p>
            <p>But I will conclude my anſwer, and this firſt reaſon,
<note place="margin">1 Joh. 2.18. &amp;c.</note> with applying of a paſſage of St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> upon that place; <hi>Little childrens it is the laſt time, and as ye have heard that Antichriſt
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:64659:11"/>ſhall come, even now are there many Antichriſts. They went out from us, but they were not of us; for if they had been of us, they would no doubt have continued with us. Non poſſunt exire foras niſi Antichriſti, &amp;c.</hi> None, ſaith he, can go out of the Church but <hi>Antichriſts:</hi> They which are not contrary unto Chriſt cannot go forth; for he which is not contrary unto him doth abide in his Body, and is accounted a member. Who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever do not abide with us, but do go out, it is manifeſt that they are Antichriſts: And how is that to be proved? by their lye: Who is a lyer, but he that denieth that <hi>Jeſus</hi> is the <hi>Chriſt?</hi> Let us ask the ſeveral Hereticks of our times; what Heretick do you find that denieth <hi>Jeſus</hi> to be the <hi>Chriſt?</hi> Some (as he proceedeth) are gone out from us, and are become <hi>Donatiſts:</hi> Let us ask them whether <hi>Jeſus</hi> be the <hi>Chriſt,</hi> they preſently confeſs that <hi>Jeſus</hi> is the <hi>Chriſt.</hi> If therefore he be the <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt</hi> that denieth <hi>Jeſus</hi> to be the <hi>Chriſt:</hi> neither can they call Us <hi>Antichriſts,</hi> nor We them, becauſe we both confeſs the ſame. Wherefore, if neither call one another <hi>Antichriſts,</hi> we are not gone out from one another, we remain in Unity. But if we remain in unity; <hi>[Quid faciunt in hâc civitate duo altaria?]</hi> What mean two divers Churches in this City? <hi>[Quid faciunt diviſae domus?]</hi> What means the ſcattering of houſes? <hi>[diviſa conjugia?]</hi> husband and wife going two waies? <hi>[Quid facit communis lectus &amp; diviſus Chriſtus?]</hi> What meaneth this, that husband and wife are one in all but <hi>Chriſt?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Vult nos fateri quod verum eſt. An ipſi a nobis exierunt, an nos ab ipſis? ſed abſit, ut nos ab ipſis: Habemus enim teſtamentum domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicae hareditatis: Dabo tibi gentes hareditatem tuam: Quisquis hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ic haereditati non communicat, fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ràs exiit.</note> ſaith he, we muſt confeſs the truth. Are they gone out from Us, or We from them? God forbid that it ſhould be We from them; for We have the Teſtament of the Lords Inheritance, ſaying, <hi>I will give thee the Nations for thine Inheritance:</hi> whoſoever doth not communicate with this Inheritance, he is gone forth, and in fact and deed he is againſt Chriſt, though in word he do confeſs him. Such as act prepoſterouſly for Chriſt, and for the Cauſe of Chriſt, do but hinder where they make a ſhew to help, and pull down where they ſeem to build, or at leaſt build that which muſt be pulled down again, although they may poſſibly work
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:64659:11"/>with a good intention. But under this pretext there are many that do act from a different temper; which is one thing that our Brethren will be loth to bear; and therefore I will com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound with them for ſome abatement, that they may hear my next reaſon with the more patience.</p>
            <p>The true Church doth earneſtly deſire the return of her ſcattered and divided Members,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>2</label> by reaſon of her ſenſe of pain, and loſs, through ſuch diſſipation or diviſion: ſhe doth not feel, nor yet conceipt herſelf to be compleat without them, but rather maimed and deprived.</p>
            <p>The Phyſical Philoſopher ſaith, that <hi>dolor eſt ſolutio continul,</hi> pain is the ſolution or diviſion of that which was entire: As if it be a wound or rent, the parts are diſtermined from one another; if it be a bruiſe, the circling of the blood and ſpirits are interrupted: from which enſueth an ach or a ſting in the parts affected, or in the whole body, which is called pain. The Members of the Church may be divided, either by a bruiſe, or a wound, or a diſlocation, or in a word by diſmembring; in each of which degrees the Church doth ſuffer a divers pain or loſs. It is a bruiſe, when hereſies are broached, which tend to diviſion: It is a wound when a breach is made there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by. It is a diſlocation, when the Church comes by this means to loſe her influence, ſo that ſhe cannot move her limbs. It is a diſmembring, when the part unſound is either cut off by cenſure, or cutteth of its ſelf by raſhneſs. Becauſe I cannot touch upon all the caſes, there is a threefold pain, and a three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold loſs, which are worthy to be mentioned.</p>
            <p n="1">1. There is a pain of inflammation in the Church, when certain Tenents are given out that tend unto a new way, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the conſtitution or eſtabliſhment: And though in truth there be no time nor place wherein the enemy doth not caſt abroad the wild-fire of hereſie and ſchiſm; yet at ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times the minds of men are more diſpoſed than at others, to receive theſe ſparks, and to kindle in combuſtion. When the <hi>Arrian</hi> Hereſie firſt brake forth,
<note place="margin">Socr. l. 1. c. 6.</note> there aroſe every where (ſaith my Hiſtorian) no ſmall tumult; for then a man might have ſeen not only the Preſidents and chief Rulers of the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, inveighing one againſt another with opprobrious terms,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:64659:12"/>but alſo the lay-multitude ſevered aſunder into two parts, the one favouring the one ſide, the other favouring the other ſide; and the caſe became ſo hainous, and ſo ſhameful, that the Chriſtian Religion came to be derided openly, even in the publick Plays and Shews. And has it not happened thus a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us, by reaſon of ſome factious Doctrines that have been far and wide diſperſed? We allowed a great latitude unto opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion before, according unto every mans ſenſe and conſcience; and now we come to tax other points, which tend to diviſion, and do not come within the Verge of that latitude (though the maintainers of them do pretend indeed that they ought to do) We muſt not doubt to inſtance in a few particulars inſtead of all the reſt. What could follow but a miſerable inflammation, when there were ſubjects apt to receive ſuch o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions as ſome of theſe? <hi>viz.</hi> That our National Church is no true Church, or if it be a Church in any ſenſe, that it is improperly ſo called: That it hath no power of binding or looſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; That her Members have no obligation to continue in her Communion, but rather to come forth from it, even as out of <hi>Babylon:</hi> That there can be no Communion with Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations that are ſo mixed, and which cannot chooſe but to continue ſo, whiles they are under ſuch a government: And in fine, that the work of Reformation doth require the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verting of ſuch a Government, and ſetting up of ſome other more agreeable (as the parties grieved do conceive) to the word of God: or, if they cannot do that, <hi>aedificare imperium in imperio,</hi> to ſeparate from the Church, and exerciſe among themſelves ſuch divers diſciplines as the ſeveral free people will admit. What a buſtle have theſe opinions made through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Land, rending in the Body before they rent from it?</p>
            <p n="2">2. There is a pain of convulſion, which is a rending in the bowels of the Church by ſuch as do yet continue in her body, and hold with her Communion, but are ready to gnaw their paſſage out by their working. Thus it was when ſome of our Members were taught, as if it were hardly lawful to hear ſome of our Miniſters, at leaſt not to live under their Miniſtry; to go abroad far and wide to hear; and to communicate only
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:64659:12"/>in ſome choicer Congregations; yet abhorring ſeparation, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe as then (it may ſeem) there wanted ſtrength to bring forth thoſe iſſues which the Teachers did deſire, hoping better of the product then the event did ſhew.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Laſtly, there is a pain of diſtraction, which the Church doth ſuffer, and which hath long continued; partly whilſt the ſeveral dividing Members ſtruggled with one another, which ſhould give the law unto the reſt; at leaſt, which ſhould have preeminence; partly ſince the Church hath reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered ſome conſiſtency with a poor ſubſiſtence (howſoever en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vied) through Gods eſpecial grace and mercy (till we do for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feit it again by our miſcarriages) in the ſeveral Banners that are hung out from divers Forts, refuſing to be reduced upon any reaſonable terms that can be offered. Which pain is the more grievous to the Church, the Mother of peace, in that ſhe is both forced to contend with her own children, and is alſo rent by her own bowels of compaſſion, and fearful of the iſſue.
<note place="margin">Judg. 21.</note> As when the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> had vanquiſhed the Tribe of <hi>Benjamin</hi> (which we have not yet done, fearing to proceed unto extremities.) <hi>The people of Iſrael came to the houſe of God, and lift up their voices and wept ſore, and ſaid, O Lord God of Iſrael, why is this come to paſs in Iſrael, that there ſhould be to day one Tribe lacking in Iſrael?</hi> This alas! is our complaint at this day; not a Tribe or two, but they ſpeak as if of twelve we had but two remaining. They ſpeak it may be according to their paſſions, but we with the pain of compaſſion added unto this of our diſtraction, muſt needs acknowledge and lament the ſad diminutions which we have ſuffered, and do ſtill ſuffer in our Body, which having loſt its Members, can neither go with eaſe, nor take repoſe in any poſture: And this brings me from the pain of ſenſe to the pain of loſs; to mention alſo the threefold loſs, which the Church ſuſtaineth by theſe diviſions.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The firſt is the loſs of power unto edification; our di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions have plucked up the flood-gates, and made profane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs overflow like a deluge: and behold they ſay, look what the people are whom we have left! who could have abode a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them? whereas the people was not ſuch before, whilſt
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:64659:13"/>the laws might be executed, and the Diſcipline of the Church was revered, and the gravity of Miniſters was held in ſome reſpect! Is not all Religion (or at leaſt the power of it) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come contemptible? ſo that now it is in vain to go about to reſtrain any mans practice by fear of cenſure; he doth not value it; or to bind any mans conſcience by the power of any ſound doctrine: He hath received diſſolute principles: He is not to be moved by love or fear. Our diviſions have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moliſhed all theſe, and layed them low; and men do now pretend a binding conſcience to commit ſuch ſins, as we were bound in conſcience to reſtrain them from, if we were able; fot ſince our diviſions have erected that plea of liberty of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, men of no conſcience have ſerv'd their ends of it: and if all parties now were to be numbred, the greateſt part would be found to be that which is of no party, but to live as they liſt, without a law, and (I had almoſt ſaid) without God in the world too. Beſides all this; has not Popery had as fair play as it could wiſh, and ſo ſtrange an encreaſe in a ſhort time, as to amaze us now, and ſtrike a real terror, not into vain apprehenſions (as they have made uſe of it, as a ſcare-crow heretofore) but into the ſobereſt minds amongſt us? And we may thank our diviſions for this too. Yet our Brethren that have divided us, have ſtill declared themſelves to be no leſs enemies unto Popery than unto Prophaneneſs. But ſee how they have been over-wrought, and to what a paſs we are all brought, who do but want the power of the Papiſts to unite us in Religion, and to reduce us unto better manners, and to more obedience unto Governments! Oh ſad diſeaſe, that needeth ſuch a remedy! from ſuch a ſad and fearful revolution, Good Lord deliver us.</p>
            <p n="2">2. A ſecond loſs is that of Interceſſion: when the men of <hi>Nineveh</hi> joyn'd unanimouſly in one requeſt, God Almighty favour'd them with an eminent return of mercy; yet they were aliens from the Covenant of promiſe. But did ever the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> cry unto the Lord, and he did not hear them? Did they ever murmur and he did not plague them? What ſhould I ſay, as a mortal man, about the unſearchable judgments of Almighty God? If we agree in any one deſire,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:64659:13"/>as for peace and ſettlement, can we agree to come into any one place, or to take with us words to ask it at his bounteous hands? Can we ask it with any fervour, whilſt we have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves about the terms, whereupon we do deſire it? or can we expect that he ſhould anſwer cold, uncertain, and lukewarm Petitions? Is not this the cauſe that we are ſpiritually diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>armed, even as the <hi>Philiſtins</hi> dealt by the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> ſo that there is neither ſword nor ſhield amongſt us, whereby we may prevail with God for any bleſſing upon us, or our Poſterity? That the Heavens are as braſs, which our divided prayers can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not pierce? That ſuch clouds of blackneſs are impendent over us? But if we pray to God for divers things, ſuch indeed as are contrary and inconſiſtent with one another, what re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turns can we expect? Here is an Aſſembly, praying, down with this, down with that. There is another, praying, Not ſo Lord, but eſtabliſh this, and reſtore that: only in this they may poſſibly agree: Any thing rather than that which is. Which ſide ſhould God Almighty hear?
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Evertêre domos totas, optanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus ipſis, Dii faciles: noci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tura toga noci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tura petuntur militia,</hi> Juven. Sat. 10.</note> or with which ſhould he not be offended? Is not this the reaſon therefore of ſuch a diſtracted State? Do not the ſame pray againſt the peace and ſettlement which they do pretend to deſire? And hath not God (ſometimes) anſwered their importunity, by giving their own requeſts, to their utter diſappointments, that they might be convinced of their own vanity, in their inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medling ſo much as they do with his Providences? And yet they will not learn to be wiſe unto ſobriety: but ſtill they ſeem never to pray with more ſpirit (ſuch as it is) than when they pray againſt their Brethren.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The third and laſt loſs which I ſhall mention, is alſo moſt invaluable; our charity is diſtracted and abated, which the poor do ſadly feel of our civility is diſturbed, ſo that men do not dare to become free in converſation, till they have ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently proved the company: our neighbourly love is abated, and inſtead of a friend, which one had before, it may be he hath an enemy, or but a faint-hearted kindneſs, or an hollow pretence of ſome good will, conſiſting rather in ſome good wiſhes than he were but ſuch at his former friend would have him to be, that he might love him, whoſe love (at beſt) is not
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:64659:14"/>without its rigour. But I will alſo ſpare to dilate my ſelf on this point, that (at leaſt) on one ſide charity may remain the ſounder.</p>
            <p>The laſt reaſon why the Church doth ſo earneſtly deſire the return of her ſcattered and divided Members,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>3</label> is the great benefit and content that ſhe ſhould find therein; which is,</p>
            <p n="1">1. The delight of love: The <hi>Shulamite</hi> was paſſionately beloved for her good parts and beauty, which the Daughters of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> do acknowledg when they ſay, <hi>Return, return, ô. Shulamite, that we may look upon thee:</hi> and the <hi>Shulamite</hi> underſtands no other when ſhe anſwereth, <hi>What ſhall ye ſee in the Shulamite?</hi> We acknowledge the like, and we will tell you (with your favour) what we would ſee in you. We would ſee, and be partakers of your knowledge, and of your gifts of underſtanding in the Scriptures: We would ſee your zeal for God, and for his Sabbaths, and for his Ordinances: We would ſee your charity towards your neighbour, whom you would not have ſeen heretofore to ſin (at leaſt to commit a ſin unto death) but you would have aided, and admoniſhed him, howſoever you think your ſelves to be excuſed (ſince) of being your Brothers keepers: We would ſee the ſtrictneſs of your lives, and of thoſe of your families: We would hear your Readings, Prayers, Inſtructions, Catechiſings, and other good Conferences that were wont to be there, fit to edifie, and to miniſter grace unto the hearers: We would over-hear your private prayers and devotions in your Cloſets, where you were wont to ſtrive with God for the pardon of your ſins, and for the obtaining of his holy Spirit, to ſanctifie you throughout in body, foul, and mind: We would ſee your firſt love again (if it be poſſible) and thoſe <hi>fruits,</hi> which you then brought forth, <hi>worthy of amendment of life.</hi> This is the beauty, which the Church would now ſee in the return of the wandring <hi>Shu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamite,</hi> whether it be as in the dayes of old; that if ſo, ſhe might admire and cheriſh her.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The beauty of array, which hath much decayed ſince our Congregations have been diverted, our Families divided, our People ſcattered: We can no more ſee men coming with their whole Train to the Houſe of God, as they were wont
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:64659:14"/>to do: And that was a beauty in the Streets of our <hi>Jeruſalem:</hi> We cannot ſee their order here, where their ſeats are void; ſo that our Churches look like great Houſes, that are ſpecious to behold without, but being unfurniſhed within afford the colder comfort: We cannot hear their voices in his holy Temples, ſinging aloud, and praiſing God, making alſo me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lody in their hearts, ſo keeping time on earth with the Saints and Angels that are in heaven: Much leſs can we meet them, as we uſed to do, at the Lords Table, at that Feaſt of Feaſts, the only Feaſt of Loves, that Feaſt of marrow, and of wine refined on the Lees.
<note place="margin">Pſal. 42.4.</note> And <hi>when we remember theſe things</hi> (to uſe the Pſalmiſts words) <hi>we pour out our ſouls within us: for we had gone with the multitude, we went with them to the Houſe of God with the voice of joy and praiſe, with a multitude that kept holiday:</hi> Theſe are the daies that would return, <hi>ô Shula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mite,</hi> with thy return. Then if any unbeliever, or any other bearing evil will to <hi>Zion,</hi> ſhould look into our Aſſemblies, he might be apt to be ſtriken, and to be driven to confeſs, that ſurely God were amongſt us, or in the midſt of us. But now if he look in here, what ſhall he ſee but a deſpicable emptineſs? and if he go there, a more contemptible multitude, for want of order, which is <hi>the beauty of holineſs?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Laſtly, Would but our divided Members return again, as Brethren, unto the body of our Church, we ſhould then come to have the ſtrength of <hi>two Armies;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen, 49.4.</note> whereas we are now unſtable and weak as water, and cannot excel; we ſhould then become ſtrong and invincible, and might boldly write upon our banner, <hi>Deus nobiſcum, quis contra nos?</hi> God is with us, who can ſtand againſt us? The gates of hell ſhall not prevail, neither policy, nor power, nor any weapon that is form'd a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt us. We ſhould then renew our ſtrength like the Eagle; our youth ſhould return to us, as in the day when we came up out of the land of <hi>Egypt,</hi> in the beginning of the Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation: we ſhould have ſtrength within, and the bleſſings of peace with it: we ſhould become a terror unto foreign Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which do now deſpiſe us, and mark us out for a prey, in the day of their power, and of our weakneſs. Have we for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten our deliverences from the power of <hi>Spain</hi> and <hi>Auſtria,</hi>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:64659:15"/>and the <hi>Pope</hi> of <hi>Rome?</hi> our Victories in <hi>Ireland?</hi> our Aids that we were then enabled to afford to <hi>Henry</hi> (afterwards the Great) King of <hi>France?</hi> and to the (then) poor diſtreſſed <hi>States</hi> of <hi>Holland?</hi> Having at the ſame time a Superintendency over all the Councils in the Realm of <hi>Scotland,</hi> and an influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence upon divers of our Neighbours, with ſuch a firm peace at home, that we hardly read of any inſurrection, worthy to be mentioned, in four and fourty years and upwards: Nay, the benefits of that bleſſed reign of Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> did ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to propagate a longer peace unto poſterity, than ever <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bion</hi> knew before. And if we have not yet forgot thoſe flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing dayes of our renown, let us now remember that they were the rewards of an unanimous Reformation: when the heart of the people roſe as one man to eſtabliſh the Proteſtant Religion, as one Religion in the midſt of us. And oh! that any one could promiſe me ſuch another ſpirit to ariſe in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> in theſe dayes of ours, and under God, I might as bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly promiſe even greater things than theſe. But though there be but little hopes of this, and but juſt reaſon to expect and fear, that all our labour which is thus applyed is like to be in vain; yet it is our duty to deſire and endeavour it. And with that I ſhall conclude.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Return,
<note place="margin">Applica.</note> return, ô Shulamite, return, return, that we may look upon thee:</hi> You that have been offended with our Church, and have left us, that have ſadned our hearts, and weakned our hands thus long, <hi>return</hi> at laſt to comfort us, that we may look upon you with delight, and that our hearts may be ſtayed for you, and our fears ſtinted. Are you nothing mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by the force of duty, conſidering that peace and love is the Legacy which our Lord hath bequeathed unto all his follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers to the worlds end? and the <hi>great bond of perfectneſs,</hi> which his Apoſtles laboured to preſerve entire, knowing that Unity and Charity cannot be divided? Doth it nothing move you to anticipate Chriſts intention, which is our Union, and to further Satans, which is our diviſion? Are you nothing moved with the deluge of prophaneneſs, that carrieth ſuch a multitude head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long into hell, whilſt you diſpute which is the way to ſave them, and agree not on it? Are you nothing moved with
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:64659:15"/>the growth of Popery, which is like to over-run all; and if it did, would make you glad to digeſt the hardeſt morſel about which you are now ſo nice? conſidering that there is no other way in probability to prevent this, but your return into the Tents that you have left. Are you nothing moved by the judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments which have followed upon our diſſentions, and do ſtill lye upon them as a juſt puniſhment? <hi>O God,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 60.2.</note> thou haſt caſt us off, thou haſt ſcattered us, thou haſt been diſpleaſed with us, thou haſt made the land to tremble, thou haſt broken it: O heal the breaches thereof, for it ſhaketh: Thou haſt ſhewed thy people hard things:</hi> And nothing is more hard than this, that our hearts are hardned againſt the wayes of peace after all our wars and unſpeakable calamities: Our blood hath been ſhed in vain. <hi>Quintili Vare, redde legiones quas perdidiſti:</hi> O Church-diviſions, reſtore again the blood that hath been ſpilt like water on the ground, never to be recovered: Return the ſpirits which we have loſt. We have undone the Poſterity which is to come: The children yet unborn are accurſed in their Parents loins, by reaſon of our diviſions, and the iſſues that are thence to be expected: for as long as there is ſuch a temper that doth over-rule the <hi>Genius</hi> of the Nation, God, who is offended with our prayers and ſervices muſt needs with-hold that good that ſhould eſtabliſh us; and though He ſhould grant it, yet ſhould we with-hold it from one another, and ſooner rend and tear it into pieces, than to let the publick be the better for it. It can never be well with us till there be an healing, and till Reformation do begin (as was ſometimes preached to the <hi>Parliament</hi>) at the Houſe of God. <hi>To your Tents</hi> therefore, <hi>To your Tents, ô Iſrael;</hi> not for war, but for peace; not to ſet up many Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars, but to compaſs about the Tabernacle:
<note place="margin">Cant. 1.7.</note> for <hi>why ſhouldſt thou be any longer as one that turneth aſide by the flocks of thy companions?</hi> O thou that haſt turned thus aſide, haſt thou any light more than others? We are the darker for the want of it: Haſt thou any good affections more than others? We are baren and unfruitful for the want of them. Haſt thou any power to add unto the Miniſtry of the word? We are deſtitute thereof, while it ſeems to be ſpent upon ſuch as do
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:64659:16"/>the leaſt need it: Doſt thou look upon us, as being yet not fit nor worthy of thy Communion? Return and ſtrengthen us with better members (if thou haſt any ſuch to add to us) and we ſhall be thereby the more enabled to amend what is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſs. Canſt not thou ſerve God with ſo much purity and power amongſt us, as in ſeparate Aſſemblies? Remember whence thou hadſt that purity and power, and reſtore the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit thereof to the ſame Church from which thou didſt at firſt receive it: Remember that heretofore thou couldſt be richly edified in the boſom of the ſame Church, and ſince thou haſt left it, both the purity and the power (whereof thou ſpeakeſt) according to our eſtimate, is much decayed and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paired: Nay, thou calleſt that the power of godlineſs, which we take to be another thing: Thou doſt but make excuſes, not only againſt thine own duty, but againſt an invaluable priviledge, which is the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity of the Spirit;</hi> and if the Church cannot be compleat without Thee, much leſs canſt Thou be made perfect without <hi>the Body;</hi> either edified in the true faith, or love; by which alone thou canſt expect to come to that <hi>peace of God which paſſeth all underſtanding,
<note place="margin">Phil. 4.7.</note> which ſhould keep your hearts and minds through Chriſt Jeſus.</hi> Wherefore let me end my own Exhortation with that of the ſame Apoſtle in another place:
<note place="margin">Col. 3.14, 15.</note> 
               <hi>Above all things put on charity, which is the bond of perfectneſs; And let the peace of God rule in your hearts, to which ye are alſo called in one Body, and be ye thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:64659:16"/>
            <head>Some Books printed for <hi>Henry Brome</hi> ſince the dreadful Fire in <hi>London.</hi>
            </head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>DR.</hi> William Lloyd's <hi>Sermon before the King againſt the Papiſts.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>His Sermon at the Funeral of</hi> John <hi>Lord Biſhop of</hi> Cheſter.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>A Seaſonable Diſcourſe againſt Popery.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Dr.</hi> Heylin <hi>on the Creed, in fol.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>A Sermon at the Aſſizes at</hi> Reading: <hi>by</hi> Joſ. Sayer, <hi>M.A.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Mr.</hi> Stanhopp's <hi>four Sermons on ſeveral Occaſions.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Mr.</hi> Hampton's <hi>Aſſize Sermon.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>A Sermon at the Funeral of Dr.</hi> Turner <hi>Dean of</hi> Canter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury: <hi>by Dr.</hi> Du Moulin.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The Anthems of the Church.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The Controverſial Letters, or Grand Controverſie, concerning the pretended Authority of Papiſts over the whole Earth.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Popery Manifeſted, or the Papiſt Incognito, made Known.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Toleration diſcuſſed.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The Vindication of the Clergy.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The Godly mans Companion.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The Guide to Heaven, with a Brief Rule of Life.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Manuductio and Coelum, <hi>or a Guide to Eternity, extracted out of the Writings of the Holy Fathers and Antient Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers. Writen originally in Latin by</hi> John Bona.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
